e
e e
so you remember the date or you know
denomination is push back yeah make an
announcement push back you know two
months well
not well to uh to March
3rd yeah okay back to the next Community
yeah all right good evening and welcome
I call to order this meeting of the
committee of council for Monday February
3rd 2025 Mr Harris can you please call
the RO of
members yes Mr vice
president Mr mad here Mr royya here Mr
Glee here miss Craig here M Diaz here Mr
hsh here and president
B council president Bay's excuse this
evening a few friendly reminders please
note this meeting is being live streamed
and recorded today's committee meeting
does not have a scheduled public comment
period but counselors May invite public
comment after each item on their agenda
if you are making a public comment
please do uh so at the microphone and
state your name and address for the
meeting record also please be sure to
silence any cell phones or devices I'll
hear a motion for the approval of the
December 2nd 2024 committee meeting
minutes motion to approve second second
a motion in a second Mr
Harris Mr M uh Mr Roy
I Mr Glee I M Craig I Mr di I Mr hsh
I we'll start off with the Personnel
committee councelor klees thank you Mr
Vice President uh the personal committee
has two items on the agenda but the
first item is pushed back to the next
committee
meeting and the second item is the
nomination for
reappointment to the city revitalization
and improve mement Zone Authority Shelby
Norman she currently serves on the board
and she expresses her willingness to be
reappointed and uh I have to mention
also that she was recommended by Senator
Senator Scott Martin due to her
experience with the community and
economic
development are there any questions or
comments from other members of the
committee
from other members of
council from the
public hearing none so I'm going to make
a motion to move this nomination to our
full cons meeting second all in favors I
I thank you that concludes the personal
committee Mr Vice President thank you
councelor colleagues uh we'll go into
the finance committee uh we have three
items on the agenda for today uh we'll
start off with Administration resolution
number
1225 uh which is amending the
supplemental pension plan for the city
employees um uh this specific uh item on
the agenda needs to be updated uh the
supplemental supplemental pension plan
for the city uh we reviewed this a year
ago and adding the firefighters to the
plan at that time uh but we did not
update the match contribution for police
according to the current collective
bargaining agreement with them uh the
supplemental Pension Plan stats uh
states that a match of
25% um but we have been paying 35% based
on the contract we need to update the
pension plan to reflect that uh I'll
invite director Campbell if there's
anything additional that we need to add
to the
resolution I don't have a lot additional
to add um this is to reflect the current
am uh matching contribution for police
officers hired on or after January 1st
um so we missed it when we updated it
last year so we are updating it
now thank you director Campell any
questions from the committee or full
councel any questions from the
public great uh I'll move uh to a motion
to move Administration resolution number
12225 um to full Council the next full
council meeting second motion second all
those in favor I
I next item on the agenda is
Administration resolution number 13 2025
this is exonerating the 2024 Water and
Sewer charges for city-owned and related
properties uh typically every year we
exonerate the water and sewer charges
for city-owned and related properties uh
this is the annual occurrence for those
exonerations U I'll invite director
Campbell for any additional commentary
uh yeah so um as Council Roy already
stated this is an annual resolution um
it's done because uh the city tracks
Waters who are us usage at City
properties this is mostly to detect
leaks or unusual usage but we don't Bill
ourselves for this usage so the charges
are exonerated annually to clear them
from Financial accounts um I do want to
note that there's two properties on this
list that are not city-owned um and that
is the library and the fire line at the
Lancaster Airport
um the Water and Sewer Service to the
library is considered an ink kind
contribution from the city uh and the
service to the airport is done in
exchange for the airport providing the
city use of its large capacity
snowblowers in case of a major
snowstorm thank you director Campbell
any questions or comments from the
committee or full
Council any questions from the public
with that I'll motion to move
Administration resolution number 13 2025
to the next pool council meeting second
a motion in a second all those in favor
I
I the next item on the agenda is an
update on the 2025 Bond debt issuance
and director Campbell will be giving
that
presentation yes thank you um I will try
to keep this brief tonight um and but
just wanted to give an overview this
evening so at the March 3rd um Council
committee meeting which is next month
we'll be introducing an ordinance for a
2025 General obligation Bond um at that
time um we'll have a detailed list of
projects included in the bond in in
March and Daryl pek who's our Financial
Consultant from Concord public uh
financial advisors will attend that
meeting to provide details of the
financing at that meeting we'll also
look at debt repayment potential
amortization schedules and effects on
the operating budget um and which some
of those effects would start uh with
with some of the funds in
2026 for tonight I want to give just an
overview of the bond and a very high
level idea of the projects that will be
included in the bond all of these
projects come directly from the 30-year
Capital plan that we reviewed on a
couple of different occasions last
November um this General obligation Bond
will include a propos a proposed total
of 55.3 million in debt financing this
financing is divided between three of
the funds so the general fund and then
two Enterprise funds the water fund and
the sewer fund uh the storm water fund
and the solid waste and recycling fund
are not included in the 2025 General
obligation Bond so the breakdown of the
financing would be as follows and I um
did send councelor Royo uh this
breakdown and I believe he sent it out
uh just uh about an hour or so ago so my
apologies for the lateness on that um so
there will be about 19 million from this
bond that goes towards the general fund
the main buckets of projects included in
this area are uh I I will give uh a few
of those here uh six of those um
resources for our Parks uh because the
parks and open space master plan was
approved in the fall of 2024 works now
needed to implement that plan so
approximately 3.5 million of this
funding will go to support that
work um there will be continued
implementation of the active
Transportation plan um so this includes
again a a few different projects which
you will see detailed out more in March
but this approximately 1.9 million um
some of the funding will go towards the
vision zero work approximately 2.7
million of the bond will be used to fund
contining work on our vision zero plan
um about 5.9 million will go towards
various RightWay improvements this
includes continued work on South Duke
Street uh Street Scapes on Anna judana
and numerous s signal upgrades
throughout the
city um about 1.6 million would go for
um some ongoing maintenance to our
facilities including roof repairs for
some various buildings um it will also
include some upgrades to the Welcome
Center that are um starting now and and
um some other general maintenance needs
um and finally we've designated about
3.4 million toward expanding
efficiencies for our operations center
uh we need to build a new salt shed
among other things we have concerns that
the current one U won't be able to
withstand the weather for much longer
and it also includes um cost for
upgrading storage both for equipment and
for our
archives so moving on I'm going to
actually jump to water next um there's
about 17.6 million of the bond that'll
be designated for water uh this consists
of four main areas um the first and and
biggest is the water transmission main
which um we have discussed a few
different times approximately 10 a half
million will be designated for this work
um this is the main transmission line
from the sasana river uh the line is
currently past its useful life um
requires us to replace it to ensure that
the water continues to flow at the
capacity that we need to serve to serve
all residents um next is just some uh
General water quality improvements uh
this category is about 3.6 million and
includes a few different projects that
are focus on maintaining or improving
water quality U and again those will be
outlined in more detail in March um
another category is the lead service
lines uh replacement of those we've
discussed this numerous times as well in
the past we're currently um working with
some federal requirements to get the
lead service lines replaced and we've
designated about one and a half million
for this work in the bond um and then
finally we're designating approximately
2 million towards design costs for the
work uh to lower to lower P fos rates um
which is another requirement um that
we've discussed in the past and then
lastly uh just quickly I'll I'll talk
through the Wastewater fund um so that
is about 18.7 million of this Bond and
that is uh what's designated for
Wastewater or sewer there's six main
categories of projects that uh this
funding will be used for um the largest
fund the largest portion of this funding
which is approximately 7.6 million will
be used toward work being done to
separate our combined sewer system
systems
um this is uh work that combines the
storm water or that separates the storm
water runoff from sewer outfalls um that
are currently combined because of the
infrastructure um that we have in the
city and then um and that funding is
actually used for three different um
sewer separation project
projects we've designated about 4.7
million of the bond to be used for
projects related to the long-term
control plan or the consent decree um
the plan should be approved by the end
of uh this year I believe and we have uh
limited time to actually implement the
plan once it's approved so this funding
will go towards
that um the uh Anor robic digestor uh
one of the longer term plans that the
DPW team has brought to council uh in
the past is to install an aerobic
digestor um which would be a more
efficient use for us than the current
Wastewater system that we have um we
don't anticipate that this will be built
before 2028 so we're not including
construction funding in this fond but we
it will take a significant amount of
design work um and so that is
approximately one and a half million of
this um there is uh some collection
system improvements uh some expansion of
the collection facilities and
Rehabilitation that we need to do so
that's approximately 3.65 million and
then two smaller items um one is that we
are looking to um purchase a camera
truck um and I'm not exactly sure of all
the details on that uh director Campbell
might be able to help with that but this
is a uh my understanding is it's a truck
that can help us to assess all the
current conditions of our collections um
infrastructure um as well as help with
some GPS and GIS
preparations um and then we have we do
have about 500,000 um uh towards
emergencies um that would be needed in
the in the bond so as I mentioned at the
beginning this is intended tonight as a
very broad overview um of the upcoming
Bond funding we will have more details
both written and as a verbal report on
March 3rd um you'll see a full list of
projects and we can answer any specific
questions that we might not be able to
answer this evening um we'll also have
the opportunity to discuss this again
two more times at Council meetings when
the first and second readings of the
ordinances are are heard um in March um
or potentially April depending on the
timing of the of the bond work and bond
auction um so I welcome questions this
evening and if I don't have exact exact
answers I'll make sure that I follow up
on March 3rd as
well thank you director Campbell any
questions from the committee or Council
councilor Craig thank you Vice um I'd
like to know a little bit more about the
truck yeah I'm gonna ask the other
director Campbell to come up on that one
so thank you very much for that question
this is in Aid of trying to better
understand and evaluate the horizontal
infrastructure the truck allows us to uh
less
invasively uh identify the condition and
materials of some of the Wastewater
infrastructure that's throughout the
system without having to do what we call
potholing or digging into every location
in two or three locations it's a
fraction it's it allows us to do that
work at a fraction of the cost we have
as you know thousand tens of thousands
of customers and we're trying to update
the current infrastructure to have a
better sense of for Capital planning
long-term capital planning what is
necessary uh be able to plan for uh
replacing
uh uh Wastewater lines before they
actually break Etc Etc so that's what
this is that that's what this is about
it's it's not only the truck but it's
the camera equipment and some of the the
instrumentation that's required to be
able to see underground or to less
invasively uh excavate to be able to get
the information we
need thank you very
much thank you councelor Craig any
additional questions or comments from
the committee or Council councelor Med
thank you vice president Royal and thank
you for uh presentation director
Campbell I'm sure we'll get more to this
in the March meeting in the first second
reading but can you just talk a little
bit about the timeline of some of these
projects and compare to the distribution
of some of the funds through the uh the
dispersement of some of the funds um as
it relates to the projects yeah um I
will I will say something very briefly
and then maybe have uh a director
Campbell come up again um we are uh
as you may remember from the capital
budget um presentation back in November
um we actually have sort of a 30e layout
for some of the projects um but we're
really uh focusing on the first six
years of that and so these um funds
really are on what we feel like uh
projects that we feel like will be
completed or at least started in the
first three years of that so from now
until 2028 do you want to add anything
to that yes
thank you again that's a very accurate
representation what what that 30-year
plan shows is the work that needs to get
done from now until the end of that 20
or 30y year period depending on which
fund it is um we anticipate each of
these projects that are listed or each
of these categories of projects that are
listed to either be underd design over
these next three years or design and
start construction so large projects
which like the digestor which is tens of
millions of dollars we're looking at it
taking the better part of two years to
do the design of that alone we would not
be starting construction before 2028 but
we would need to have all the design
funds in place so that we can go after
the the loan
documentation um and uh where they
generally require full design documents
as well as permitting to be able to get
that work done we would be coming to you
in 2028 for the bond to fil fulfill
those large some of those larger
projects some of the smaller projects
whether it's Parks master plan
implementation Etc some of those we
anticipate that we can do the design and
actually get construction started or in
some cases actually completed within
this three-year period And so u under
the parks master plan implementation
there are several parks that are that
are included in that uh which we'll go
into detail with next month
um and the intention would be to be able
to do the design work get the permitting
and be able to get the construction at
least started in SE several of those
parks for vision zero that's much more
of a
rolling uh set of work it's it's the
more modest interventions such as neck
downs and uh pedestrian interventions uh
delineators Etc and and Street markings
uh as well as some of the initial design
for uh um for uh two-way
restoration those are multi-year
projects but as you know Vision Vision
zero is targeted to be to make this huge
in investment before uh 2030 the goal is
to be able to make the difference by
2030 so in s in its simplest form all of
this all of these are projects where the
funds need or we fully expect the funds
to be needed and expended Within These
first three years we have been very
meticulous in saying if it's if it in
two things if it's a project that we
think is going to be more expensive or
that we will not be able to afford The
Debt Service of at this point can it be
deferred and that's been put into
hopefully uh the 2028 Bond
or on a on a priority list that may
actually have to take it off the
long-term list but most of the things
that are on this list are required
either by uh uh for uh for functionality
Andor for uh for audit purposes these
are requirements especially in water and
wastewater these are requirements of the
utilities in the Pu to be able to make
and maintain the water qualities that we
deliver um but each of these are with
are within this window of of uh the
three
years thank that helps a lot and just my
follow-up question is you know given
that these are some of the first
threeyear plans um are we confident in
our ability to Serv as the whole Deb
given the need for additional bonds
after the planning or design phase I
will defer to Tina um and a lot of it
has been what do we believe we have the
The Debt Service capacity to take on we
have actually truncated or reduced the
scope of many of these projects in
anticipation of staying within the
limits that we can afford but it does
mean that there are C certain items
especially in water and wastewater where
we may have some harder questions as we
go into the future because those are
very expensive and are needed
irrespective of our ability to Inc
incorporate them at this
moment Tina yeah um I think you uh
summarized that very well I I will just
add we have been looking at this um like
like Steve said with debt targets both
for 2025 and 2028 based on um what we
can afford so looking at kind of that
future borrowing as
well thank you and I appreciate your
follow thank you councelor m any uh this
councelor deal in regards to um the
items will this be discussed to the
public I mean how is this going to be um
available for the public to ask
questions I mean you you're asking or
you're going to say that it's going to
to be presented in March but I think
that the community should know this
prior to
March yeah I
um I think it's I mean I think it'll be
advertised that it's in March but yeah I
would also just say that the master
Parks plan implementation does include
um all of the engagement that we did
that lays out um the plans for many of
the parks that are on the list Vision
zero is similar as part of the act of
Transportation which has been approved
by city council um and the vision Z and
active transportation both both of those
things and then um as it relates to uh
the other aspects um The Welcome Center
funding um and
other general maintenance facilities
that is all part of our um facilities
condition assessment work that um DPW
has been doing as part of its long-term
control plan so I would say on the major
projects for the general fund the
majority of them have been vetted um
through the public and through this and
through Council body as it relates to
Water and Wastewater um are you asking
about those councelor Diaz or just the
first basically looking at the fact that
this is we're looking at a debt and bond
financing needs that's that's mostly
what I'm looking at I know some of them
are we had already voted on that prior
to or we're basically looking at in the
future especially with the EP uh
mandates that we have to follow through
with that but that's a large amount and
that's why I'm I'm asking if that was
actually brought up to um to the
community um because I think they should
know yeah yeah I mean I think this is
the open forum for the community um we
you know will provide all of that um in
in March before it's actually voted on
so there will be opportunities for the
community to speak into it as well and I
think that's also the the benefit of the
adoption of the home R Charter requiring
the long-term capital plan uh to be laid
out for the public so that there is uh
more broad awareness of the types of
Investments that are required in our
water Wastewater and storm water um
infrastructure to meet um state and
federal regul
regulation so that's going to be a much
bigger conversation because uh it is
breathtaking the the amount of money
that is
necessary um and to address our
infrastructure needs and also um the um
federal and state
requirements the other excuse me the
other thing I wanted to add is that we
did when um I believe it was in the the
December presentation the November
presentation we had our my Deputy
directors and we went into greater
detail about the background that
supports the reasoning behind what was
going on why what kind of replacement
are we talking about what kinds of
regulatory things do we have to fulfill
Etc so one might actually go back to
those those are online for review if one
wanted to to look at more detail and be
and refresh we've we've made a conscious
effort to try to to present this over
time and not just spit it all at people
all at once so I do I'm I'm a aware that
it's a lot of stuff to try to absorb and
there are documents and YouTube videos
online that you can you can review to
see what we were talking about and yes
it will be as Tina says it will be
presented again not at that level of
detail but project by project in the
sequence of what is necessary for these
next few years to get us from where we
are to where we need to
be my last question and regards to um
these projects do we have anything
included that was already added in
regards to the grants is there any
grants that we had added into this
because I'm just trying to figure out
what the difference between the debt and
also the minus the grants yeah um so the
one that I will point out is the vision
zero work um so that is uh most of that
the I believe it's 2.1 of the 2.7
million um is actually for matching
funds for the grant that we receive for
the Safe Streets for all um we're
currently unclear if we'll receive all
of that Federal funding but since the
funding was already awarded to the city
we're continuing to plan um that we will
receive that funding so that's why we
included the
match my last question I'm sorry I I
just thought of this just because I know
that there's a lot um there's a big
question mark on what the federal
government is going to be doing um have
you received anything or any notices of
grants that that may have been already
either denied or that they are going
forward with
it um I'll say that it's been pretty
unclear at this point um we are
understanding that anything that was
contracted is moving ahead so that's
what we're kind of going with at this
point but we're still trying to kind of
determine that I think um yeah
thank you very
much any additional questions or
comments from
Council from the
public thank you director Campbell for
the presentation and director campb for
that comment additional
commentary that'll conclude the finance
committee uh we'll move on to the public
works committee councelor hsh thank you
vice president Oro Public Works
committee has uh four items on the
agenda this evening however one of them
um well actually I'll I'll start with
resolution number 10 um which is
authorizing a cost sharing agreement
with Manheim Township for Marshall
Avenue roadway
repairs um essentially preparing to add
bicycle infrastructure and among other
things um and repairing some sections uh
of the Marshall Avenue Corridor um and
given that the Border with the city and
manam Township is you know very kind of
chaotic I don't know what other word to
use for it at that area um this uh
agreement is required um director
Campbell I don't know if you have
anything you want to
add yes thank you very very much this is
this is
um to be able to do surface treatment of
roadways that are shared by both Manheim
Township and the city of Lancaster on um
Marshall Avenue between litz Pike
and uh and Juliet Avenue it's
approximately 82% of the roadway is
owned by the city about 17 plus% of the
roadway is owned by Manheim Township in
order to get the work done we need to
work cooperatively and that requires
having a resolution that we are working
cooperatively
all of the paperwork has already been
conducted Manheim Township has already
signed on this much of this work will be
self-performed and therefore the cost of
doing this work is really quite minimal
um it's 50 50 about $50,000 for the city
of Lancaster about uh $122,000 for the
city of for the for Manheim Township and
much of the work by being self-performed
we're primarily just getting uh
purchasing the materials and
coordination so it's a modest piece of
work this the signature for this
resolution is the last thing that allows
us to go forward so that the work will
commence this spring and will be
completed by
summer thank you very much uh director
Campbell and um now I understand you
know when I read the amounts in the
resolution I don't think it came up in
our conversation this morning but um uh
in the resolution it said something of
the effect of like the city is uh paying
82% of that roughly $60 to $70,000 cost
and now you just said that that's the
percentage of the roadway the city owns
versus Township so I see where that
comes from Yes um but I think it's
helpful for the public to understand
that as well um I'll open it up to
comment from the public works committee
or full
Council uh any comment or questions from
the
public hearing on I'll make a motion to
move resolution 10225 to our full
meeting of Council on uh February 11th
so all those in favor
I um the next item on our agenda um my
understanding is that um we seeking to
table this at this
time
um is is that correct my understanding
is that this had been this was to have
been taken off the agenda
uh because action had already been taken
taken on this and unless there was going
to be something new in terms of funding
or Grant changes there was no need for
it to come back back before this C this
body okay um thank you uh is there any
action required uh
parliamentarian order no action required
it's simply not moving forward
okay um with that I will move to uh the
last two uh resolutions on the Public
Works committee agenda because I believe
they are related um resolution 16
authorizing an agreement with Railway
auditing and Management Services and
resolution number 17 authorizing an
agreement with uh Norfolk Southern
Railway company um this is for some of
the city's uh water infrastructure um or
actually waste water I believe um it is
water water okay um happening in uh in
Columbia borau um and it's essentially
an administrative uh step for us
to um authorize this agreement but I
will let director Campbell speak to this
more yes very very good thank you very
much both of these are very much the
same even though they are two different
Railway entities with whom we are
working in order to estab in order to
finish or do the work related to the
long the large diameter pipe we have to
go under Railway right of ways in order
to have access to railway R of ways we
need to enter into a license agreement
with each of those entities one of them
being the railway auditing and
Management Services and another one
being
the um the norick Southern Railway both
of these intersections are within
Columbia burrow very close to the Susana
River and and these rights of way would
be uh we would be sharing the right of
way we have a license to share the right
of way um so that we can fulfill the
large diameter pipe through that section
of the infrastructure it's these are
these peculiar little areas where we
have to work with or get around or get
through or get under the railway lines
and they have their own authority what
they need and require of us is a a
resolution that indicates that the city
of Lancaster is in agreement agement
that we are licensed that we are
entering into a license agreement with
them and the cost of that per license
permit is
uh
$5,500 for and I mean it
$5,500 for the railway auditing and
Management Services piece and
$2,500 for the Norfolk Southern Railway
piece
uh thank you very much director Campbell
I will open it up to comment or question
or comment from the public works
committee or full
Council uh councelor C thank you coun
thank you for the
presentation um what would be the role
of the city in those projects will the
city be involved in ongoing oversight of
those projects very very good question
all we we still we still would be the
ones in charge of the design and the
construction of doing this work it's
just that we just like if we were going
across your your own personal property
we need to have in this case a license
agreement to use their right of way
otherwise if it were through your
property we would need an easement from
you to be able to have access and the
cost of getting that license agreement
is the permitting application fees which
is what is being requested here here but
yes we will be in charge of the design
and and construction getting the pen
vest loans getting the getting the work
performed to our satisfaction to our
standards and to meet our requirements
sounds good thank you no further
questions thank you
cons thank you Council please um any
other questions or comments from full
councel or the
committee any comments or questions on
the
public um hearing none I'll actually
make a motion to move resolutions number
16 and 17 together um onto our full
Council agenda on February 11th so move
all those in favor
I thank you very much that concludes the
Public Works committee thank you thank
you councelor H uh we'll move to the
community planning committee councelor
Craig thank you Council Vice um
community planning has one item on the
agenda this evening Administration
resolution 14
2025 adopting substantial amendments to
the C
cdbg Consolidated plan and action annual
action
plan and I see we have the ladies
setting up here so I'm going to
assume that is a good assumption thank
you councelor
Craig good evening mayor counselors I'm
pleased to introduce to you this evening
U Miss Jen Rumble she is our new
Community Development administrator and
she started in September with a lot of
Grant management experience in the
nonprofit world and we were very glad to
have her jump into this very extensive
substantial amendment process for uh the
Community Development block
grants um I wanted to note for you
before Jen starts what is in your pack
maret we are recommending changes to
each of the annual action plans for cdbg
for 2021 2022 2023 and 2024 as we near
the end of our fiveyear Consolidated
plan and we included the entire original
plans with the highlights in yellow so
there are the changes are limited and
those are highlighted in yellow but the
whole documents are there The Originals
with the in yellow um so that is what
you have before you this evening and I
will pass it over to
Jen thank you sorry hopefully I didn't
push the button all right uh thank you
Madame mayor and S Castle I'm pleased to
speak to you tonight about the Community
Development block grant substantial
amendment process hopefully my screen
will continue to glow up there okay uh
before we get into the details of the
substantial amendment I wanted to give
you a brief overview of the cdbg program
the cdbg program which is administered
by the Department of Housing and Urban
Development provides annual grants to
entitlement States cities EXC a minute
is it possible to speak up a little
bit sorry my apologies is this
better yes okay thank you the cdbg
program which is administered by the the
housing of urban the admin
administration of Housing and Urban
Development provides annual grants to
entitlement States cities and counties
to help develop viable urban communities
in providing funding to support the
provisions of decent and affordable
housing the creation of a suitable
living environment and the expansion of
economic
opportunities principally to to benefit
low to moderate income persons HUD
authorizes cdbg funding to be spent on
the
El following eligible Community
Development categories affordable
housing and preservation and production
public infrastructure improvements
Public Services Economic Development and
planning and
administration we use these guidelines
for planning programs and allocating our
cdbg dollars to support Community
Development in our city this process
follows a five-year goal focused
Consolidated plan planning cycle that
provid provides HUD with a big picture
unified strategy of the city's main
Housing and Community Development goals
and planned projects at the onset of
each fiveyear planning cycle the city
must submit a Consolidated plan
outlining its needs the market
conditions and overall goals of The
Five-Year Plan additionally each year
within the fiveyear Consolidated
planning cycle the city must submit an
annual action plan for Meeting those
goals for with the funding approved for
the projects based on the grant
allocation for each year the
Consolidated plan and the annual action
plan are shared with the public for
comment sent to city council for
approval and adoption and then submitted
to HUD for their review and
approval now I'm going to summarize why
we came before you with a substantial
Amendment tonight a substantial
amendment is required in three
situations when we make a substantial
budgetary change when they change when
we change the purpose scope location or
beneficiaries of an activity or when we
reallocate funds from one eligible
category to another the specific details
of what constitutes a substantial
budgetary change is outlined in our
City's 2021 to 2025 Consolidated action
plan and or I'm sorry in our citizen
participation plan the threshold in our
city is $50,000 or 50% % of the budget
whichever threshold is lower the sum we
are asking to move today is
$50,000 which created the need for a
substantial amend is sorry is greater
than $50,000 which created the need for
tonight's substantial amendment
process before we review the Amendments
we are proposing let's examine the
impact of the city's cdbg entitlement
funding and anticipated upcoming funding
since 2021 our budget has been reduced
about 5% annually these changes can be
attributed to federal budget changes
shifting in federal funding priorities
changes in populations in terms of
number of people or even concentrations
of people who fall below the poverty
line and um while we have not yet
received our 2025 allocation uh if cdbg
continues to be funded as it has in the
past and there are no federal funding
freezes we anticipate our funding will
be about
1378 million with our program Revenue
included adjusted to
1.43 million our team is watching for
daily updates and will continue to
adjust spending as needed in this new
context the city of lancas identified
four priority Community goals during the
community engagement portion of our 2021
to 2025 Consolidated plan despite small
shifts in our annual funding we were
able to continue to fund each of those
four four major priorities Over The Last
5 Years with cdbg entitlement funds
therefore our 5-year Consolidated plan
is not being amended as we continue to
be in line with those four major goals
um I can't tell if everyone in the back
is able to see so I'm going to go over
the categories briefly maintain quality
affordable housing is at large uh red
42% increase affordable housing
opportunities is the lower gray at 16%
promote neighborhood quality of life is
I guess kind of a darker gray or lighter
gray at 26% and that's 1% slice there is
expand economic
opportunities the 15% uh is not listed
in one of our four um major categories
but that is for planning and
administration uh if you look at the pie
chart you can see more than half so the
16 plus the 42% 58% of our investment is
in increasing quality affordable housing
opportunities and maintaining quality
affordable housing
opportunities some of the funding
activities in certain are capped in
certain percentages from our overall
funding these caps limit our ability to
carry funding over a year to year which
is the primary reason that we have
brought a substantial amendment to you
tonight first let's discuss the items
that we are proposing an increase in
funding recently the city of Lancaster
received new new grants which reti which
require a total of
$199,000 in matching funds from
cdpg first
$70,000 we're requesting towards the new
match for a $3 million healthy homes
program Grant the remaining
$120,000
$129,000 we are requesting towards the
match for a new
7.75 million lead Hazard Reduction
Program Grant we're also requesting the
reallocation of 70 $5,000 to support the
Bay Street Community Garden
project this money was primarily
allocated from the unspent allocation
for the Lancaster wreck hbac Center at
their old building which is now not
needed we are pleased to continue to
partner with the Lister rec center for
this new community garden
activity last we are looking to
reallocate
$35,200 for affordable housing Solutions
the need for maintaining and increasing
affordable housing continues to be a
significant concern in the city of
Lancaster the city plans to increase its
investment in affordable housing through
a competitive process seeking eligible
projects that may include activities
such as construction of new Housing Home
Ownership assistance an acquisition
Andor rehab of existing housing for the
purposes of increasing affordable
housing for low and moderate income
individuals
most of the decreases you see here are
due to caps on administrative and public
service dollars if we do not spend in
these categories we cannot carry them
over to the next year because caps apply
every year if there are Staffing
vacancies those monies must be
reallocated into uncapped categories we
are requesting to move
$4,750 from the done program manager
position to their Staffing vac cancy in
2024 the funds were not spent down in
this category we have funded this
position again in
2025 if the cdbg allocation is received
as expected we requesting to move
9,654 from the police Social Work
program in addition to Staffing
vacancies and spending caps some of the
police social work hours that were
anticipated to be charged to the police
Social Work Program were not eligible
due to Geographic restrictions for
example the downtown area is excluded
geographically third we are requesting
to move
$129,450 from building clo enforcement
these dollars were originally allocated
during the covid-19 pandemic however
building code revenues increased to a
point where cdbg funding was no longer
required to support the program and last
we are requesting to move 100
66,1 34 from program from planning and
administration which is entirely due to
Staffing vacancies and caps on
funding in summary the total number of
dollars we are seeking to reallocate
over this 5-year allocation con plan is
584,000 of the 700 7.7 79 million
entitlement allocation or approximately
14% I'm sorry no approximately
7.59% should the 2025 allocation become
less certain we will revisit city
council as needed to examine our
options so a reminder for those who do
not have the entire substantial uh the
entire uh substantial Amendment plans in
front of them we have a hard copy
available at City Hall we have digital
copies that are available on our website
and public comments will be open until
March
3rd I wanted to give some quick overview
of some upcoming dates we're
anticipating in early March we will be
presenting our Consolidated annual
performance and evaluation report our
Caper where we summarize the outcomes
and expenditures of the cdbg funds from
the previous year in June we expect that
we will be presenting our 2025 annual
action plan a summary of our key goals
and objectives for the 20125 cdbg
entitlement and um along with a list of
metrics of how we plan to measure those
objectives and last as you know 2025 is
the last year in our 2021 to 2025
Consolidated plan so between April and
August of this year we're going to be
entering the citizen participation
portion of our 2026 to 202030
Consolidated plan and we're looking
forward to working with all of you our
community members local nonprofits local
Champions and our most vulnerable
population in planning for our City's
future so thank you for the opportunity
to present and we are pleased to take
any questions you may have about our
proposed
approach thank you ladies for your
presentation I'll open this up to the
committee for questions and full
Council just a comment um just a comment
U just want to thank the city for
continuing to prioritize uh housing and
affordable housing um and home
repair um and continuing to push every
dollar that we can towards that um it's
important
so thank you councelor Craig and thank
you guys for the presentation um just a
question about some of the moves that
were made due to Staffing levels not
being filled such as Department of
neighborhood engagement or you know the
city program Administration um in future
plans you know if these um positions are
restaff you know will we go after those
dollars to uh cover you know those
positions because I do think and I think
that there some of these positions are
very popular such as the department of
neighborhood engagement or you know uh
Small Business Development and I just
wanted to know what the plan were you
know try to get those positions refilled
and how the cdbg grants could help
that let me take that yes thanks for the
question that's a good question through
these moves these are addressing um past
vacancies not vacancies that are coming
up are positions that are being cut and
so um through the Consolidated planning
process those were priority areas and
Priority Staffing and so those remain
consistent uh the issue has more been
that when there has been a vacancy for a
considerable amount of time in the prior
Year we're not able to use that funding
for that same position the next year
because of capson funding and so that
position those positions have been
continued to be funded in the next
year's in the same cdbg uh with the same
cdbg
allocation thank you and then in regards
to the police Social Work Program being
uh geographically only for the or not
being allowed in the downtown investment
area can you just expand on that and
just kind of if you just kind of
re-explain uh the police social work um
aspect of it
sure so cdbg one of the main um
components is to make sure that we are
spending in low to moderate census
tracks or with low to moderate income
individuals and we have to choose one or
the other of these methodologies to
ensure that we're serving low and
moderate income individuals with each
and every activity that we do in the
case of police social worker we chose to
allocate These funds based on geographic
area so that if the police social
workers are responding in low to
moderate income census tracks primarily
in the southern part of the city uh
those are the activities that are
covered by the police social worker so
when they are responding in census
tracks that are not geographically low
primarily low or moderate income
individuals then their time cannot be
covered by
cdbg uh so this was not
uh we maybe anticipated more of their
time being covered initially but we have
not cut those positions just only a
portion could be funded with the cdbg
funds uh thank you and I look forward to
working with you guys on the engagement
around the 2026 to 2030 plan wonderful
Council Craig uh excuse me just a quick
comment um I'll abstain from voting on
this item just because the organization
that I work for assets is listed um as
an organization in the action plan so
I'll abstain from voting thank you are
there any further comments or questions
from Council as a whole if I may um
counselor Craig um in regards to the
funding for the
CBD and housing is is that including
some of the shelters does any of that
funding go to any of the local shelters
that we have good question that you want
me uh the only funding that I saw that
went to the shelters was from 2021 that
was part of the ESG
allocation so homeless shelters and
service for homeless individuals is out
is funded through the emergency
Solutions Grant or ESG funding uh for
which we received entitlement funds in
2021 one but not since and those same
activities are not eligible through cdbg
for cdbg funding because they are funded
with Federal entitlement ESG funding so
cdbg cannot fund shelter activities or
activities for the
homeless but isn't that considered
someone that is
unhoused that needs
housing yes the so someone who is unh
housed would definitely need housing the
affordable housing development Solutions
is for the construction of new housing
or the rehabilitation of affordable
housing so it's more about the
infrastructure of the housing than it is
about service to that particular
individual and that is in the Nuance of
what is allowable or unallowable in the
federal regulations and how many houses
are are actually listed for the CBD job
dollars to um repair
do you have a stock number how many we
have funded with cdbg how many are going
to be funded and the repairs being done
is there a stock number a number of
houses or apartments that's a good
question uh primarily with cdbg we have
funded the rehabilitation of affordable
housing for a home ownership and rental
through partners with purpose which was
formerly part of Lancaster City Housing
Authority and also with Saka who they
they renovate homes and then sell them
to uh
homeowners so we have funded those two
programs uh those two partners with this
funding previously and the subsidies in
recent years have been extensive for
each and every rehabbed house because of
the conditions U many times uh blighted
or EX in extremely poor condition and so
so even the 300,000 now that we are
allocating to this uh it is but a drop
in the bucket for what is needed for
affordable housing in this category um
but thank you councelor hirs as well for
pointing out every dollar we could that
we didn't need in other categories we
funnel back into that affordable housing
um but our average costs sometimes
they're 150 to 200,000 per unit for
Rehab of uh existing housing so it's
expensive
so so you're looking at probably
repairing what three houses with that
particular money depends on the
condition of the house I would say no
more than three with that with that
additional allocation um but over the
course of the whole all the action plan
and all the money um we allocated 1,
157,000 and we've already
done I want to say nine to 10 uh
properties with the money that we've
already allocated into that program so
we will come back next month with the
Caper uh for what we accomplished in
2024 and we'll have all the cumulative
totals there H but with that million
dollars those that's what we've already
done with with those dollars so far in
the Consolidated plan thank
you are there any further questions from
the public
wonderful thank you Miss geyser and I
apologize I forgot your name already Jen
Rumble thank you so much thank you Jen
rum thank you for having us and we look
forward to presenting to you our
accomplishments next month it will be um
more interesting and exciting than
simple administrative task of
reallocating dollars so we look forward
to that next month thank you thank you
so much um I'll make a res uh motion to
move this to full Council on the 11
second all those in favor I Council Vice
that concludes Community
planning thank you Council Craig uh we
will now move to the committee of the
whole uh we have two um agenda items for
this evening first is Council resolution
number 9 2025 recognizing Black History
Month I'll turn it over to councelor
Craig thank you Council Vice um it is
February this month of the year and here
we are at Black History Month again so
I'm going to um first ask is there
anybody here that would like to speak to
the the resolution
afterwards then I will proceed in
reading the resolution into
record um the res the city resol council
resolution number n 2025 introduced by
me councelor Craig adopted by Council a
resolution of the city of the Council of
the city of Lancaster designating
February 2025 as Black History Month in
the city of Lancaster and recognizing
resistance to Injustice by
African-Americans throughout Lancaster's
history whereas since 1976 February H
February has been recognized in the
United States as Black History Month and
nationally ATT national attention has
been focused on the history of
African-Americans the civil rights
movement and efforts to advance the
place of African-Americans in society
and whereas the theme of the
2025 National recognition of Black
History
Month is African-Americans and labor and
whereas all types of work volunteer
involuntary skilled unskilled has been
foundationally to to the experience of
black people in the United States and
whereas early black residents of
Lancaster were enslaved here and labored
for others such as those who built the
and operated General Edward H Rock
Rockford
estate and whereas in
in the
by in and by the mid 19th century free
blacks had become entrepreneurs
profiting from their own labor such as
Lumber Merchants William whipper and
stepen Smith and Lydia Hamilton Smith
who owned rental properties in Lancaster
and Washington DC and were all involved
in the Underground Railroad and where as
members of the Lancaster Lancaster's
black community and their white allies
organized to resist unfair practices in
unemployment including Abraham polite
Maran Gibson Brewbaker and Laura
Carter who organized the Lancaster
branch of the NAACP in
1923 and in the summer of 1963 the
NAACP organized protests of downtown
Lancaster's department stores over
discriminatory hiring practice because
black employees at those stores were
relegated to jobs as janitors
and elevator operators and
whereas other leaders of the Lancaster
branch of the nwacp including the
Reverend Phillip Aku Robert a Cooper
Ashley s Dudley Jr the Reverend
Alexander stefin Kenneth boast and
Reverend Ernest Christian and Ken
Kenneth abery Betty Tomkins publicly
publicity the secretary of the NAACP and
Ruby cook bohi
Payne who served for nearly 30 years as
the leader of of Chrismas adct Center
and whereas black leaders labored in
Academia and create created a doc
document black history Lan in Lancaster
including Frederick Reed the first black
male teacher in the school district of
Lancaster and along I of Franklin
Marshall College Hazel I Jackson who
spent Friday afternoons in the 1950s
outside the office of the school
district of Lancaster's of Lancaster
superintendent before being hired as the
district's first black female teacher in
1961 and founded the black cultural
celebration at Millersville University
in
1970 Dr Rita Smith wayale who founded
the African-American studies program at
Millersville and Dr LeRoy Hopkins who th
who thought his through his
research lectures and articles in the in
the Journal of Lancaster County's
Historical Society has elevated black
history of Lancaster and schools in L
Lancaster where later re schools in
Lancaster were later renamed in honor of
Hazel I Jackson and Dr Rita smithwood
whereas bethl
African-American Episcopal Church
founded in
1817 and Incorporated in
1848 and other religious congregations
of predominantly black members have
provided spiritual spiritual social and
Civic support to lancastrians
for to lancastrians and before the Civil
War to Black Freedom Seekers traveling
through Lancaster under the protection
of the Underground Railroad Network
whereas Henry Norwood Barney Yu
nationally an
International Champion in track in track
events and winner of one gold medal and
two silver medals in the
19848 Olympics was recognized by the
cities by lanc the city of Lancaster in
the naming of Yu Plaza whereas Dr Carter
Woodson and and historian who earned a
PhD degree from Harvard University and
later taught at Howard University
founded the association for the study of
negro life and history in
1915 after being barred from the
American historical
Association and in 1926 founded his his
black history week the the origins of
Black History Month celebrated annually
in February and whereas Lancaster has
long been a place of welcome for those
seeking religious religious Liberties
and has sought to give up to to live up
to the principle of Liberty for all and
must continue to strive to reach that
goal and and now therefore be it
resolved by the city council of
Lancaster City of Lancaster that during
Black History Month and every month city
council calls on all
lancastrians and to respect and honor
the sacrifice of those who have
struggles for the rights of
African-American to Justice For Justice
and
equality there you go that was rather
long
but that is our black history resolution
I look it it is long and I look forward
to reading it every every year but I'm
about to lose my voice so that concludes
that thank you councelor craigan I
appreciate you reading the resolution uh
any questions or comments from F
Council from the
public with that I'll motion to move
resolution number 9 2025 to full Council
second all those in favor I next item on
the agenda is the administration
resolution number 11 2025 which is
authorizing a flag raising at City Hall
to Mark pride month uh this resolution
um was brought to us uh through an
application by the Lancaster Pride
Association which has submitted its
application to the city of Lancaster in
a timely manner that is requesting that
the pride flag be flown at City Hall on
June 2nd 2025 with a backup date of June
3rd 2025 in case of inclement
weather any questions or comments from F
Council any from the
public with that I'll motion to move
Administration resolution number 11 2025
to full Council second all those in
favor great that concludes our committee
of the whole we'll now move to the
clerk's report uh Mr Harris I believe
you submitted that to us in writing I
did yes great um uh I'll ask Council to
review the uh written report um with
that I will conclude uh city council
committee motion to adjourn second
second all those in favor I meeting
adjourned thank
[Music]
you team a much better